<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://luhuadong.com</id>
    <title>成为自由人 • Posts by &#34;一起看影片&#34; category</title>
    <link href="https://luhuadong.com" />
    <updated>2023-03-02T04:56:58.000Z</updated>
    <category term="商业" />
    <category term="成长" />
    <category term="日记" />
    <category term="创业" />
    <category term="家居" />
    <category term="互联网" />
    <category term="读书笔记" />
    <category term="工程师" />
    <category term="爱" />
    <category term="名言" />
    <category term="奋斗" />
    <category term="信息世界" />
    <category term="管理" />
    <category term="程序员" />
    <category term="职场" />
    <category term="人生" />
    <category term="物联网" />
    <category term="城市规划" />
    <category term="Python" />
    <category term="教孩子学编程" />
    <category term="创客" />
    <category term="比赛" />
    <category term="科技向善" />
    <category term="英语" />
    <category term="学习" />
    <category term="环保" />
    <category term="碳中和" />
    <category term="种植" />
    <category term="健身" />
    <category term="地理" />
    <category term="城市" />
    <category term="气象爱好者" />
    <category term="指南" />
    <category term="自律" />
    <category term="思维" />
    <category term="健康" />
    <category term="Hexo" />
    <category term="科普" />
    <category term="可持续" />
    <category term="能源" />
    <category term="职业" />
    <category term="时间管理" />
    <category term="工作" />
    <category term="总结" />
    <category term="慈济" />
    <category term="RT-Thread" />
    <category term="开源" />
    <category term="思考" />
    <category term="生活" />
    <category term="猫" />
    <category term="幸福" />
    <category term="修身" />
    <category term="写书" />
    <category term="milestone" />
    <category term="地铁" />
    <category term="Markdown" />
    <category term="计划" />
    <category term="股票" />
    <category term="理财" />
    <category term="投资" />
    <category term="财富" />
    <category term="保险" />
    <category term="纪录片" />
    <category term="自由" />
    <category term="电影" />
    <category term="TED演讲" />
    <category term="时间" />
    <category term="心理学" />
    <category term="无线电爱好者" />
    <category term="亲密关系" />
    <category term="农业" />
    <category term="励志" />
    <category term="演讲" />
    <category term="游泳" />
    <category term="蔬食" />
    <category term="电台主播" />
    <category term="WordPress" />
    <category term="垃圾分类" />
    <category term="零废弃" />
    <category term="低碳" />
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/grit-the-power-of-passion-and-perseverance.html</id>
        <title>【TED】坚韧不拔：激情和毅力的力量</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/grit-the-power-of-passion-and-perseverance.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;演讲题目：Grit: The power of passion and perseverance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;演讲者：Angela Lee Duckworth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;中英双语版本&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#中英双语版本&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 中英双语版本&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=35473820&amp;bvid=BV1Fb411c7J7&amp;cid=62190294&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;无字幕原版&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#无字幕原版&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 无字幕原版&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=35473820&amp;bvid=BV1Fb411c7J7&amp;cid=62190447&amp;page=2&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;同名书籍&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#同名书籍&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 同名书籍&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;英文：《&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuYW1hem9uLmNvbS9Hcml0LVBhc3Npb24tUGVyc2V2ZXJhbmNlLUFuZ2VsYS1EdWNrd29ydGgvZHAvMTUwMTExMTEwOA==&#34;&gt;Grit: The Power of Passion and Perseverance&lt;/span&gt;》&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;繁体中文：《&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuYm9va3MuY29tLnR3L3Byb2R1Y3RzLzAwMTA4Njc5MzE=&#34;&gt;恆毅力：人生成功的究極能力&lt;/span&gt;》&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="TED演讲" />
        <updated>2023-03-02T04:56:58.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/who-killed-the-electric-car.html</id>
        <title>【纪录片】谁消灭了电动汽车（Who Killed the Electric Car?）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/who-killed-the-electric-car.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=289405784&amp;bvid=BV1Wf4y167N8&amp;cid=304238328&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这是一部 2006 年上映的纪录片，该片探讨了电池电动车，特别是通用汽车的 EV1 电动车的产生、有限商业化及随后的消亡。剖析电动汽车在该时代死去的原因，将责任不仅归咎于消费者和汽车生产商，还归咎于布什政府和石油业。&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="纪录片" />
        <updated>2021-11-01T04:52:47.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/revenge-of-the-electric-car.html</id>
        <title>【纪录片】电动汽车的复仇（Revenge of the Electric Car）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/revenge-of-the-electric-car.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=414110662&amp;bvid=BV1aV411z7VL&amp;cid=218525092&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这部 2011 年拍摄的纪录片讲述了特斯拉（Tesla Motors）如何历尽艰辛挺过金融危机，深入探讨全球电动汽车复苏的景象。&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="纪录片" />
        <updated>2021-11-01T03:41:36.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/ted-you-dont-need-more-than-two-years.html</id>
        <title>【TED】改变自己，只需要两年时间</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/ted-you-dont-need-more-than-two-years.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;视频&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#视频&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 视频&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don’t Need More Than Two Years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=883417381&amp;bvid=BV1TK4y1b77M&amp;cid=199198207&amp;page=1&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;中英文对照&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#中英文对照&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 中英文对照&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;两年可以做什么&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years is nothing, but at the same time, a lot can be accomplished in two years. You can try a sport you’ve always wanted to start, and become a great at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两年时间不算什么，但在这段时间里，我们可以做很多事情。你可以尝试练习一项你一直想要开始的运动，然后成为一名高手。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start a morning routine, and affect your mood and stress at a deep level. You can meditate for a few minutes per day, become more self-aware and change the way you react to problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你可以开始制定某项早间习惯，它会从深层次影响你的情绪和压力。你每天可以冥想一分钟，这样就可以加强自我意识，提高应对问题的能力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start a business and make it a big success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你可以开创一项事业，并让它走向成功。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years is nothing and extremely easy to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but with small actions , substantial commitment and consistency, you can make it count, a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两年的时间不算什么，也很容易浪费掉，但只要有微小的行动、实质性的付出和坚持，你就可以让它变得更有价值。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years being passive is a blink of an eye. Two years moving towards goals every single day is plenty of time. It’s just a matter of perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;消极度日，两年转眼即逝。每天有目标地前进，两年就意味着更多的时间。这仅仅是看问题的角度不同而已。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing that cannot be accomplished in two years with enough effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果足够努力，没有什么事情是两年内不能实现的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start something you’ve wanted to do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;开始做你一直想做的事情。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re not too old for the things you were dreaming of doing when you were a kid. You can still do extreme sports if you wish to. You can start playing a musical instrument. You can become a photographer. In two years from now, you’ll be great at it if you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;对你年少时的梦想来说，你永远不会太老。只要你想，你还是能去做极限运动。你还是能去学习乐器。你还是能成为一名摄影师。从现在起的两年时间，只要你真的想要，你就能变得很厉害。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t let your past indicate who you are. You don’t have to be the same person you have always been. Don’t let fear control you. Don’t let the social standards conform you. Age is just a number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不要让你的过去决定你是谁。你也不必一直和以前一样。不要让恐惧支配你。不要让社会标准囚禁你。年龄只是个数字而已。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should all empower our uniqueness and fight against our own limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我们所有人都应赋予我们独特性，并与自己的局限作斗争。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing things you love on daily basis even for a few minutes, you’ll learn to enjoy the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每天去做你喜欢做的事情，哪怕只有几分钟，你也会享受这个过程。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The days will become more than just a means to an end. You’ll see yourself evolving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每天会变得更有意义，不会被虚度。你也会看到自己的进步。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be in control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;保持自律&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the choice between feeling great, energetic and in a positive mood, versus feeling sleepy and moody, what would you choose? It’s just a choice which combined with small, even tiny actions like reducing meat or alcohol consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果你能选择让自己感觉棒棒的，精力旺盛，乐观向上，亦或是疲惫着，喜怒无常，你会选哪一个？这就是个简单的选择，再加上小小的行动比如少吃肉或少喝酒.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or simply drinking more water, walking the stairs or biking to the office, you can do wonders. It’s not about the end goal, it’s about daily actions towards it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;再或是多喝点水，爬楼梯或骑脚踏车上班，你就会创造奇迹了。这么做不是为了简单地达到目标，而是为了每天都能够朝这个方向进步。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also the reason why morning routines, or ten minutes daily meditation sessions are bringing such great changes in terms of mood, productivity, stress management, ect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这也是为什么早间的习惯和十分钟的每日冥想都能带给人巨大的改变，比如情绪、生产力和压力管理能力的改善。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replace TV shows and movies by documentaries and books. Minitor your days more getting control of how you spend your time. Take back the control of your health, mood and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;用纪录片和书籍取代电视节目和电影。加强监督自己的日常，控制自己利用时间的方式。夺回你对健康、情绪和时间的掌控权。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practive gratefulness. See the results in two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;学会感激。两年后见分晓。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silence your ego&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;压制你的自负&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be kind with people. Start with your family, don’t go mad one more time. Stop judging, see the good in them, and remember that you love them more than anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;善待他人，再也不要和家人发火。停止批判，看见他们好的那面，并记得你爱他们超过一切。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your working life, being kind and nice can bring you more respect from people who surround you than being bossy and aggressive. Learn to say ‘No’ often (for the right reasons), people will accept it more and value your ‘Yes’ more, because your times’ value will increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在职场上，与人为善，相比发号施令和争强好胜，这会让你周围的人更尊重你。学会在正当理由下多说 “不”，这样人们会更容易接受，且更看重你说的 “好”，因为你的时间价值会增加。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be scary to be respected. It’s about building trust and healthy long term relationships. Try this and in two years from now your reality will be so different. Silence your ego, love and trust others enough for two years, harvest for ten years or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你不用通过变得吓人去获得尊重。重点是要建立起相互信任且健康的长期关系。试试看，从现在开始起的两年，你的生活将会变得大不同。用两年时间去压制你的自负，去爱和信任他人，十年甚至更长的时间你都会因此受益。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set long term goals and do small actions everyday towards them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设定一个长期的目标，然后坚持每天即便是微小的行动。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a lot to do with setting goals, but goals without actions are just wishes. The easiest way to reach goals is through daily and consistent small (even tiny) actions. It’s all about consistency, commitment, and regularity. Success is not an event, it’s a process and a mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这和目标的设定有很大的关系，但光有目标没有行动就只能是美好的愿望而已。最简单达成目标的方法就是，每天都坚持微小的行动。一切都在于要建立一致性、要坚持付出和养成规律。成功不是一个偶然事件，它是个长久的过程和心态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small actions are putting you in the position of succeeding. Small actions make huge differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;微小的行动能让你走向成功的道路。微小的行动能带来巨大的改变。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at yourself in the mirror in two years and you’ll think ‘that was quick’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两年后在镜子中看看自己，你会想 “时间过的真快”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every day counts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;每一天都很重要。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="奋斗" />
        <category term="TED演讲" />
        <category term="时间" />
        <updated>2021-09-07T14:47:18.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/The-Story-of-Aaron-Swartz.html</id>
        <title>【纪录片】互联网之子（Aaron Swartz）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/The-Story-of-Aaron-Swartz.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=16549975&amp;bvid=BV1rx411V75r&amp;cid=26994578&amp;page=1&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
        <category term="互联网" />
        <category term="纪录片" />
        <category term="自由" />
        <updated>2021-03-05T17:43:41.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/revolution-os.html</id>
        <title>【纪录片】操作系统革命（Revolution OS）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/revolution-os.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=796140504&amp;bvid=BV1iC4y187nT&amp;cid=235560964&amp;page=1&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;非常经典的有关自由软件运动的纪录片&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cDovL3d3dy5yZXZvbHV0aW9uLW9zLmNvbQ==&#34;&gt;http://www.revolution-os.com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="开源" />
        <category term="纪录片" />
        <category term="自由" />
        <updated>2020-06-17T06:43:59.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/ted-why-30-is-not-the-new-20.html</id>
        <title>【TED】20岁到30岁，是你最不可挥霍的光阴</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/ted-why-30-is-not-the-new-20.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;视频&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#视频&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 视频&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why 30 is not the new 20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=54802233&amp;bvid=BV1B4411K7Rb&amp;cid=95852081&amp;page=1&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;中英文对照&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#中英文对照&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 中英文对照&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was in my 20s, I saw my very first psychotherapy client. I was a Ph.D. student in clinical psychology at Berkeley. She was a 26-year-old woman named Alex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;记得见我第一位心理咨询顾客时，我才 20 多岁。当时我是 Berkeley 临床心理学在读博士生。我的第一位顾客是名叫 Alex 的女性，26 岁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Alex walked into her first session wearing jeans and a big slouchy top, and she dropped onto the couch in my office and kicked off her flats and told me she was there to talk about guy problems. Now when I heard this, I was so relieved. My classmate got an arsonist for her first client. (Laughter) And I got a twentysomething who wanted to talk about boys. This I thought I could handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第一次见面 Alex 穿着牛仔裤和宽松上衣走进来，她一下子栽进我办公室的沙发上，踢掉脚上的平底鞋，跟我说她想谈谈男生的问题。当时我听到这个之后松了一口气。因为我同学的第一个顾客是纵火犯，而我的顾客却是一个 20 出头想谈谈男生的女孩。我觉得我可以搞定。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I didn’t handle it. With the funny stories that Alex would bring to session, it was easy for me just to nod my head while we kicked the can down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是我没有搞定。Alex 不断地讲有趣的事情，而我只能简单地点头认同她所说的，很自然地就陷入了附和的状态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thirty’s the new 20,” Alex would say, and as far as I could tell, she was right. Work happened later, marriage happened later, kids happened later, even death happened later. Twentysomethings like Alex and I had nothing but time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex 说：“30 岁是一个新的 20 岁”。没错，我告诉她 “你是对的”。工作还早，结婚还早，生孩子还早，甚至死亡也早着呢。像 Alex 和我这样 20 多岁的人，什么都没有但时间多的是。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before long, my supervisor pushed me to push Alex about her love life. I pushed back. I said, “Sure, she’s dating down, she’s sleeping with a knucklehead, but it’s not like she’s going to marry the guy.” And then my supervisor said, “Not yet, but she might marry the next one. Besides, the best time to work on Alex’s marriage is before she has one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但不久之后，我的导师就要我向 Alex 的感情生活施压。我反驳说：“当然她现在正在和别人交往，她现在和一个傻瓜男生睡觉，但看样子她不会和他结婚的。” 而我的导师说：“不着急，她也许会和下一个结婚。但修复 Alex 婚姻的最好时期是她还没拥有婚姻的时期。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what psychologists call an “Aha!” moment. That was the moment I realized, 30 is not the new 20. Yes, people settle down later than they used to, but that didn’t make Alex’s 20s a developmental downtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这就是心理学家说的 “顿悟时刻”。正是那个时候我意识到，30 岁不是一个新的 20 岁。的确，和以前的人相比，现在人们更晚才安定下来，但是这不代表 Alex 就能长期处于 20 多岁的状态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That made Alex’s 20s a developmental sweet spot, and we were sitting there blowing it. That was when I realized that this sort of benign neglect was a real problem, and it had real consequences, not just for Alex and her love life but for the careers and the families and the futures of twentysomethings everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;更晚安定下来，应该使 Alex 的 20 多岁成为发展的黄金时段，而我们却坐在那里忽视这个发展的时机。从那时起我意识到这种善意的忽视确实是个问题，它不仅给 Alex 本身和她的感情生活带来不良后果，而且影响到处 20 多岁的人的事业、家庭和未来。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 50 million twentysomethings in the United States right now. We’re talking about 15 percent of the population, or 100 percent if you consider that no one’s getting through adulthood without going through their 20s first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;现在在美国，20 多岁的人有五千万，也就是 15% 的人口，或者可以说所有人口，因为所有成年人都要经历他们的 20 多岁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raise your hand if you’re in your 20s. I really want to see some twentysomethings here. Oh, yay! Y’all’s awesome. If you work with twentysomethings, you love a twentysomething, you’re losing sleep over twentysomethings, I want to see — Okay. Awesome, twentysomethings really matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果你现在 20 多岁，请举手。我很想看到有 20 多岁的人在这里。哦，很好。如果你和 20 多岁的人一起工作，你喜欢 20 多岁的人，你因为 20 多岁的人辗转难眠，我想看到你们。很棒，看来 20 多岁的人确实很受重视。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I specialize in twentysomethings because I believe that every single one of those 50 million twentysomethings deserves to know what psychologists, sociologists, neurologists and fertility specialists already know: that claiming your 20s is one of the simplest, yet most transformative, things you can do for work, for love, for your happiness, maybe even for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此我专门研究 20 多岁的人，因为我坚信这五千万的 20 多岁的人，每一个人都应该去了解那些心理学家、社会学家、神经学家和生育专家已经知道的事实：你的 20 多岁是极简单却极具变化的时期之一。你 20 多岁的时光决定了你的事业、爱情、幸福甚至整个世界。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not my opinion. These are the facts. We know that 80 percent of life’s most defining moments take place by age 35. That means that eight out of 10 of the decisions and experiences and “Aha!” moments that make your life what it is will have happened by your mid-30s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这不是我的看法。这些是事实。我们知道 80% 决定你生活的时刻发生在 35 岁之前。这就意味着你生活的重要决定、经历和突然的领悟，有八成是在你 30 多岁之前发生的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who are over 40, don’t panic. This crowd is going to be fine, I think. We know that the first 10 years of a career has an exponential impact on how much money you’re going to earn. We know that more than half of Americans are married or are living with or dating their future partner by 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;那些超过 40 岁的朋友不要惊慌，我想这群人会没事的。我们知道职业生涯的前 10 年对你将来的收入有重大影响。我们知道到了 30 岁的时候，超过半数的美国人会结婚或者和未来的另一半同居或者约会。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that the brain caps off its second and last growth spurt in your 20s as it rewires itself for adulthood, which means that whatever it is you want to change about yourself, now is the time to change it. We know that personality changes more during your 20s than at any other time in life, and we know that female fertility peaks at age 28, and things get tricky after age 35.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我们知道人在 20 多岁的时候大脑停止第二次也是最后一次重组，以适应成年世界的快速发育阶段。这就意味着不管你想怎样改变自己，现在就是时间改变了。我们知道在 20 多岁的时候，性格的改变多于生命中任何时期。我们也知道女性的最佳生育时期在 28 岁的时候达到顶峰，35 岁之后生育变得困难。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So your 20s are the time to educate yourself about your body and your options. So when we think about child development, we all know that the first five years are a critical period for language and attachment in the brain. It’s a time when your ordinary, day-to-day life has an inordinate impact on who you will become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以你的 20 多岁正是了解你自身和选择的时期。当我们想到孩童的成长时，我们都知道 1-5 岁是大脑学习语言和感知的重要时期。这个时期，日常的普通生活都会对你的未来道路影响巨大。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what we hear less about is that there’s such a thing as adult development, and our 20s are that critical period of adult development. But this isn’t what twentysomethings are hearing. Newspapers talk about the changing timetable of adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是我们却很少听到成年发展期，而我们的 20 多岁正是成年发展期的关键。但是 20 多岁的人却听不到这些，报纸讨论的只是成年年龄界线的变更。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers call the 20s an extended adolescence. Journalists coin silly nicknames for twentysomethings like “twixters” and “kidults.” It’s true. As a culture, we have trivialized what is actually the defining decade of adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;研究者称 20 多岁是延长的青春期。记者就引用傻傻的外号称呼 20 多岁的人，比如 “twixters” (twenty-mixters) 和 “kidults”(kid-adults)。 这是真的。作为一种文化，我们的忽视的正是对成年起到决定性作用的十年（从 20 岁到 30 岁）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard Bernstein said that to achieve great things, you need a plan and not quite enough time. Isn’t that true? So what do you think happens when you pat a twentysomething on the head and you say, “You have 10 extra years to start your life”? Nothing happens. You have robbed that person of his urgency and ambition, and absolutely nothing happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;雷昂纳德・伯恩斯坦说过：要想取得成就，你需要一个计划和紧迫的时间。这是大实话啊！所以当你拍着一个 20 多岁的人的脑袋，跟他说，“你有额外的 10 年去开始你的生活”，你觉得这改变了什么？什么都没改变。你只是夺走了那个人的紧迫感和雄心壮志，绝对没有改变什么。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then every day, smart, interesting twentysomethings like you or like your sons and daughters come into my office and say things like this: “I know my boyfriend’s no good for me, but this relationship doesn’t count. I’m just killing time.” Or they say, “Everybody says as long as I get started on a career by the time I’m 30, I’ll be fine.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然后每天，那些聪明有趣的 20 多岁的人就像你们和你们的儿子女儿一样，走入我的办公室开始说：“我知道我的男朋友对我不够好，但是我们的关系不算数。我只是在消磨时光而已。” 或者说 “每个人都告诉我只要能在 30 岁的时候开始我的事业，这就足够了。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then it starts to sound like this: “My 20s are almost over, and I have nothing to show for myself. I had a better résumé the day after I graduated from college.” And then it starts to sound like this: &amp;quot;Dating in my 20s was like musical chairs. Everybody was running around and having fun, but then sometime around 30 it was like the music turned off and everybody started sitting down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是实际听上去却是：“我马上就要三十了，却根本就没有东西展示。我只是在大学毕业时有过一份最漂亮的简历。” 或是这样：“我 20 多岁时的约会就像找凳子。每个人都绕着凳子跑，随便玩一玩，但是快 30 的时候就像音乐停止了，所有人开始坐下。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to be the only one left standing up, so sometimes I think I married my husband because he was the closest chair to me at 30.&amp;quot; Where are the twentysomethings here? Do not do that. Okay, now that sounds a little flip, but make no mistake, the stakes are very high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我不想成为那唯一站着的人，所以有时候我会想我和我丈夫之所以会结婚，是因为在我 30 岁的时候，他是当时离我最近的那张凳子。在场的 20 多岁的人呐，千万不要这样做。这个做法听起来有点轻率，但是不要犯错，因为风险很高。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a lot has been pushed to your 30s, there is enormous thirtysomething pressure to jump-start a career, pick a city, partner up, and have two or three kids in a much shorter period of time. Many of these things are incompatible, and as research is just starting to show, simply harder and more stressful to do all at once in our 30s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当很多事都被挤到你 30 多岁的时候，就会有巨大压力，在很短的时间内快速启动一项事业，挑一个城市，找到伴侣，生两三个孩子。这些事大多是不能同时完成的，正如研究表明，在 30 岁的时候要想工作生活一步到位，难度很高，压力很大。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-millennial midlife crisis isn’t buying a red sports car. It’s realizing you can’t have that career you now want. It’s realizing you can’t have that child you now want, or you can’t give your child a sibling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;千禧年后的中年危机并不是一辆红色跑车。而是意识到你不能拥有你想拥有的事业，意识到你不能拥有你想要的孩子，或者给你的孩子添个兄弟姐妹。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too many thirtysomethings and fortysomethings look at themselves, and at me, sitting across the room, and say about their 20s, “What was I doing? What was I thinking?” I want to change what twentysomethings are doing and thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;太多 30 多岁 40 多岁的人看看他们自己，看看我，坐在屋子里谈论自己的 20 多岁，“我当时都干么了？我当时都想啥了？” 我想改变现在 20 多岁人的所思所为。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a story about how that can go. It’s a story about a woman named Emma. At 25, Emma came to my office because she was, in her words, having an identity crisis. She said she thought she might like to work in art or entertainment, but she hadn’t decided yet, so she’d spent the last few years waiting tables instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这里我想讲个故事说明问题。这个故事是关于名叫 Emma 一个女人。她 25 岁的时候走入我的办公室，因为用她自己的话说，她有自我认识危机。她说她也许想从事关于艺术或者娱乐的工作，但是她还没决定。所以取而代之的是她花了过去几年的时间当服务员。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it was cheaper, she lived with a boyfriend who displayed his temper more than his ambition. And as hard as her 20s were, her early life had been even harder. She often cried in our sessions, but then would collect herself by saying, “You can’t pick your family, but you can pick your friends.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;为了减少开销，她和她的男朋友同居，一个脾气暴躁而无志向的人。正如她悲惨的 20 多岁，她早年的生活更加悲惨。她经常在谈话过程中哭泣，努力镇定下来后说 “你没办法选择你的家庭，但是你可以选择你的朋友。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well one day, Emma comes in and she hangs her head in her lap, and she sobbed for most of the hour. She’d just bought a new address book, and she’d spent the morning filling in her many contacts, but then she’d been left staring at that empty blank that comes after the words &amp;quot;In case of emergency, please call … &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有一天，Emma 走进来，她双手抱头于膝盖，然后抽泣了几乎一个小时。她刚买了一个新的通讯录本子，然后花了一整个早上的时间填写她的联系人信息。当她填到 “万一发生紧急情况，请联系…” 的时候，她没有任何人可填。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was nearly hysterical when she looked at me and said, “Who’s going to be there for me if I get in a car wreck? Who’s going to take care of me if I have cancer?” Now in that moment, it took everything I had not to say, “I will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;她几乎崩溃地看着我并说，“如果我被车撞了，谁会在那里？假如我得癌症了，谁会在那里？” 在那种情况下，我花了好大力气才忍住说 “我会。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what Emma needed wasn’t some therapist who really, really cared. Emma needed a better life, and I knew this was her chance. I had learned too much since I first worked with Alex to just sit there while Emma’s defining decade went parading by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma 所需要的并不是理疗师所真正关心的。她需要一个更好的生活，我知道这是她的机会。自 Alex 开始，我从这份工作上学到了很多，不能只是坐在那里看着 Emma 十年黄金定型期白白消逝。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So over the next weeks and months, I told Emma three things that every twentysomething, male or female, deserves to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以接下去的几个星期几个月，我告诉 Emma 三件事，所有 20 多岁的男生女生都值得听一听。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I told Emma to forget about having an identity crisis and get some identity capital. By get identity capital, I mean do something that adds value to who you are. Do something that’s an investment in who you might want to be next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;首先，我告诉 Emma 忘掉她的自我认识危机，去获得一些身份认定的资本。身份资本是指做增加自我价值的事。为自己下一步想成为的样子做一些事一些投资。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know the future of Emma’s career, and no one knows the future of work, but I do know this: Identity capital begets identity capital. So now is the time for that cross-country job, that internship, that startup you want to try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我不知道 Emma 的工作将来是什么样的，也没人知道将来的工作是什么样的，但是我知道：身份资本会创造出更多身份资本。现在是时候去尝试你想要的海外工作、实习或者新起点。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not discounting twentysomething exploration here, but I am discounting exploration that’s not supposed to count, which, by the way, is not exploration. That’s procrastination. I told Emma to explore work and make it count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我不是轻视 20 多岁的自我探索，而是轻视那些随便玩玩无所谓的探索，或者从某种意义上说那不是探索。那是拖沓！我告诉 Emma 去探索工作，让她的探索有所回报。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I told Emma that the urban tribe is overrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第二，我告诉 Emma 不要高估自己的朋友圈。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best friends are great for giving rides to the airport, but twentysomethings who huddle together with like-minded peers limit who they know, what they know, how they think, how they speak, and where they work. That new piece of capital, that new person to date almost always comes from outside the inner circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;好朋友会载你去机场，而和 “志同道合的朋友” 瞎混的 20 多岁的人，他们的交际圈、知识面、思维方式、说话方式和工作层面都被限制住了。新的资本或者新的约会对方往往是从内部交际圈之外来的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New things come from what are called our weak ties, our friends of friends of friends. So yes, half of twentysomethings are un- or under-employed. But half aren’t, and weak ties are how you get yourself into that group. Half of new jobs are never posted, so reaching out to your neighbor’s boss is how you get that un-posted job. It’s not cheating. It’s the science of how information spreads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;新的事情来自我们所谓的 “弱关系”，我们朋友的朋友的朋友。没错，半数 20 多岁的人处在失业和半失业的状态。但是另外一半的人却不是这样的，“弱关系” 正是你融入一个新的群体的纽带。有半数的新工作从来不公示出来，所以联络你邻居的老板是你找到那些未公示工作的方式。这不叫作弊，这是信息传播的科学方式。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, Emma believed that you can’t pick your family, but you can pick your friends. Now this was true for her growing up, but as a twentysomething, soon Emma would pick her family when she partnered with someone and created a family of her own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;最后一点也很重要，Emma 相信你无法选择你的家庭，但是你可以选择你的朋友。可这只是她成长时期的状况。作为一个 20 多岁的人，Emma 很快会与某人为伴组建她自己的新家庭。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I told Emma the time to start picking your family is now. Now you may be thinking that 30 is actually a better time to settle down than 20, or even 25, and I agree with you. But grabbing whoever you’re living with or sleeping with when everyone on Facebook starts walking down the aisle is not progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我告诉 Emma 现在就是你选择你家庭的时候。现在你也许会想相比于 20 岁，25 岁或 30 岁时组建家庭会更好。我同意你的看法。但是当你 Facebook 上的朋友都开始步入婚姻殿堂时，你随便抓一个人一起生活、睡觉绝对不是组建家庭的过程。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to work on your marriage is before you have one, and that means being as intentional with love as you are with work. Picking your family is about consciously choosing who and what you want rather than just making it work or killing time with whoever happens to be choosing you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;经营你婚姻的最佳时间是你还没结婚的时候，这意味要像你为了工作一样精心谋划。选择你的家庭是有意识地去选择你想要的人和事，而不是为了结婚或者消磨时光，任意选择一个正好选择你的人。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happened to Emma? Well, we went through that address book, and she found an old roommate’s cousin who worked at an art museum in another state. That weak tie helped her get a job there. That job offer gave her the reason to leave that live-in boyfriend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma 发生了什么变化呢？我们翻了一遍通讯录，她发现她原来的舍友的表妹在另一个州的一家艺术博物馆工作。这层弱关系帮助她在那里得到一份工作。这份工作给她一个理由离开她那同居的男友。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, five years later, she’s a special events planner for museums. She’s married to a man she mindfully chose. She loves her new career, she loves her new family, and she sent me a card that said, “Now the emergency contact blanks don’t seem big enough.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;现在五年过去了，她是一名博物馆特别活动策划者。她和一个她用心选择的男人结婚了。她爱她的事业，她爱她的新家，她寄给我一张贺卡写道，“现在紧急联系栏似乎不够填呢。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Emma’s story made that sound easy, but that’s what I love about working with twentysomethings. They are so easy to help. Twentysomethings are like airplanes just leaving LAX, bound for somewhere west. Right after takeoff, a slight change in course is the difference between landing in Alaska or Fiji.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma 的故事听起来简单，这正是为什么我爱和 20 多岁人打交道。帮助 20 多岁的人很容易。20 多岁就像离开洛杉矶飞往西部某处的飞机，起飞之后，一点小小变化都会影响到它最终将降落在阿拉斯加还是斐济。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, at 21 or 25 or even 29, one good conversation, one good break, one good TED Talk, can have an enormous effect across years and even generations to come. So here’s an idea worth spreading to every twentysomething you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;同理，在你 21 岁，25 岁甚至 29 岁的时候，一次好的谈话、好的休息、好的 TED 演讲，能在未来的几年甚至几代人的时间里带来巨大的影响。因此这个想法值得传达给每一个你所认识的 20 多岁人。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as what I learned to say to Alex. It’s what I now have the privilege of saying to twentysomethings like Emma every single day: Thirty is not the new 20, so claim your adulthood, get some identity capital, use your weak ties, pick your family. Don’t be defined by what you didn’t know or didn’t do. You’re deciding your life right now. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这想法就像我后来告诉 Alex 的话一样简单。我应该每天都对像 Emma 这样的 20 多岁的人说：30 岁不是一个新的 20 岁，所以规划好你的成年生活，获得一些身份认同资本，利用你的弱关系，选择你的家庭。不要被你所不知道的，从未做过的事所禁锢。你现在的作为决定着你的人生。谢谢。&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="TED演讲" />
        <category term="时间" />
        <updated>2020-05-18T14:47:18.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/patent-absurdity.html</id>
        <title>【纪录片】软件专利的荒谬性（Patent Absurdity）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/patent-absurdity.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=15221360&amp;bvid=BV1sx411u7qy&amp;cid=24774214&amp;page=1&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;官网：&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cDovL3BhdGVudGFic3VyZGl0eS5jb20vd2F0Y2guaHRtbA==&#34;&gt;http://patentabsurdity.com/watch.html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;导演、拍摄、编辑：Luca Lucarini&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;制片人：Jamie King&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;动画制作：Christopher Allan Webber&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;混音：Matt Smith&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;由自由软件基金会赞助&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;简体中文字幕制作者：阮一峰&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;本片讲述了软件专利案件以及软件专利对软件开发者和整体经济的伤害&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;本片的官方网站：&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cDovL3BhdGVudGFic3VyZGl0eS5jb20=&#34;&gt;http://patentabsurdity.com&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;本片以及本片中文字幕的使用遵循以下协议：&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cDovL2NyZWF0aXZlY29tbW9ucw==&#34;&gt;http://creativecommons&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
        <category term="开源" />
        <category term="纪录片" />
        <category term="自由" />
        <updated>2020-04-05T06:36:34.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/code-rush.html</id>
        <title>【纪录片】代码奔腾（Code Rush）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/code-rush.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;《Code Rush》是 David Winton 导演于 1998 年至 2000 年间拍摄的纪录片，记录了硅谷的 Netscape 工程师们将浏览器源代码开源，成立 Mozilla 项目的经历；同时 Netscape 也正经历被 AOL 并购的过程。本片描绘了 Netscape 的工程师们，牺牲日常生活与家庭，努力防止他们的公司倒闭的经历。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=15989846&amp;bvid=BV1rx411E7oW&amp;cid=26090372&amp;page=1&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; framespacing=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从 1998 年 3 月到 1999 年 4 月，一个独立纪录片摄制组跟随着网景公司的一个软件工程师团队，记录了他们公司和互联网历史上的分水岭。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这部纪录片详实地记录了软件工程师的生活、对写代码的热情与执着、硅谷的淘金梦、投资银行家的贪婪，以及 2000 年当时尚未破灭的互联网泡沫。虽然我们没有经历那个年代，哪怕只是过去了 20 多年，对我们来说却十分陌生。强烈推荐大家观看该影片，也许能激起你对科技行业的热情，成为这个时代的爆肝工程师。&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="互联网" />
        <category term="纪录片" />
        <updated>2020-02-03T06:45:49.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/movies/dead-poets-society.html</id>
        <title>【电影】死亡诗社（Dead Poets Society）</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/movies/dead-poets-society.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;电影简介&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#电影简介&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 电影简介&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;《死亡诗社》是美国 1989 年上映的一部剧情电影，影片展示了关于守旧与创新、现实与浪漫、新人与老人两股势力的较量。每次看都会勾起我心中的波澜，反思现在的生活，变得有力量。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=10112142&amp;bvid=BV1rx411U7xi&amp;cid=16708703&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;经典语录&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#经典语录&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 经典语录&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I went to the woods because I wanted to live deliberately… I wanted to live deep and suck out all the marrow of life! To put to rout all that was not life… And not when I came to die, discover that I had not lived…&lt;br&gt;
 我步入丛林，因为我希望活得有意义… 我希望活得深刻，汲取生命所有的精髓！把非生命的一切全都击溃… 以免在我生命终结时，发现自己从来没有活过…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don’t read and write poetry because it’s cute.We read and write poetry because we are members of the human race.And the human race is filled with passion.And medicine,law,business,engineering,these are noble pursuits and necessary to sustain life.But poetry,beauty,romance,love,these are what we stay alive for.&lt;br&gt;
 我们读诗写诗，非为它的灵巧。我们读诗写诗，因为我们是人类的一员。而人类充满了热情。医药，法律，商业，工程，这些都是高贵的理想，并且是维生的必需条件。但是诗，美，浪漫，爱，这些才是我们生存的原因。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gather ye rosebuds while ye may, Old time is still a-flying, And this same flower that smiles today, Tomorrow will be dying.&lt;br&gt;
 及时采撷你的花蕾，旧时光一去不回，今天尚在微笑的花朵，明日便在风中枯萎。&lt;span class=&#34;github-emoji&#34; alias=&#34;star&#34; style=&#34;&#34; fallback-src=&#34;https://github.githubassets.com/images/icons/emoji/unicode/2b50.png?v8&#34;&gt;⭐&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carpe diem, seize the day. Boys, &lt;strong&gt;make your lives extraordinary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 人生就应该是快乐的，要抓住每一天。孩子们，让你们的生活变得非凡起来。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want you to find your own walk right now. Your own way of striding, pacing. Any direction. Anything you want. Whether it’s proud, whether it’s silly, anything.&lt;br&gt;
 我希望你们也找到自己的路，找到自己的步伐、步调，任何方向，任何东西都行，不管是自负也好，愚蠢也好，什么都行。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No matter what anybody tells you, words and ideas can change the world.&lt;br&gt;
 不管别人怎么说，文字和思想的确能改变世界。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We must constantly look at things in a different way.&lt;br&gt;
 我们必须时刻用不同眼光来看待事物。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just when you think you know something,you have to look at it in another way.&lt;br&gt;
 当你认为你知道某件事时，必须再以不同角度看它&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even though it may seem silly or wrong,you must try!&lt;br&gt;
 即使那看来似乎愚笨或错误，你们都必须试试。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now, when you read, don’t just consider, what the author thinks, consider what you think.&lt;br&gt;
 当你阅读时，别只想到作者的见解，想想你的见解。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boys, you must strive to find your own voice. Because the longer you wait to begin,the less likely you are to find it at all.&lt;br&gt;
 孩子们，你们必须努力寻找自己的声音。因为你等候起步的时间愈长，便愈不可能找到它。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thoreau said, “Most men lead lives of quiet desperation.”&lt;br&gt;
 梭罗说，“大多数人都生活在平静的绝望中。”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a time for daring,and there is a time for caution, and a wise man understanding which is called for.&lt;br&gt;
 有时候要大胆，有时候要小心，一个聪明人知道什么时候该怎么做。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t be resigned to that. Break out!&lt;br&gt;
 别听任此事发生。要突破！&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Frost said, two roads diverged in a wood and I took the one less traveled by, and that has made all the difference.&lt;br&gt;
 劳勃佛洛斯特说过，树林里两条岔路，我选择人走得比较少的那条路，那里有天壤之别。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you noticed, everyone started off with their own stride, their own pace.&lt;br&gt;
 你们若是注意，每个人都是以自己的步幅行走。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difficulty in maintaining your own beliefs in the face of others.&lt;br&gt;
 在他人面前坚护自己的信念是困难的。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would’ve walked differently.&lt;br&gt;
 我本可以走得与众不同。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We all have a great need for acceptance. But you must trust that your beliefs are unique,your own. Even though others may think them odd or unpopular. Even though the herd may go,that’s bad.&lt;br&gt;
 我们都非常需要被认同。但你们必须相信自己的信念独一无二。纵使别人可能认为它奇异或者不入流。纵使庸俗的大众可能会说，好烂。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To struggle against great odds, to meet enemies undaunted.&lt;br&gt;
 与逆境不屈抗争，以无畏的气势面对敌人。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To be a sailor of the world bound for all ports.&lt;br&gt;
 做世界的水手，游遍所有的港口。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh,I live to be the ruler of life,not a slave.&lt;br&gt;
 我要做生活的主宰，而非奴隶。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh, to have life henceforth the poem of new joys. Let it fill your soul.&lt;br&gt;
 让今后的生命如喜悦的诗。让它充满你的灵魂。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because we are food for worms lads. Because,believe or not, each one of us in this room is one day going to stop breathing,turn cold and die.&lt;br&gt;
 因为我们是蛆虫的食物，因为不管你信不信，这间房子里的每一个人，总有一天都会停止呼吸，变冷，死亡。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
        <category term="自由" />
        <category term="电影" />
        <updated>2018-10-04T14:53:15.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
</feed>
