<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://luhuadong.com</id>
    <title>成为自由人 • Posts by &#34;演讲的力量&#34; category</title>
    <link href="https://luhuadong.com" />
    <updated>2023-03-02T04:56:58.000Z</updated>
    <category term="商业" />
    <category term="成长" />
    <category term="日记" />
    <category term="创业" />
    <category term="家居" />
    <category term="互联网" />
    <category term="读书笔记" />
    <category term="工程师" />
    <category term="爱" />
    <category term="名言" />
    <category term="奋斗" />
    <category term="信息世界" />
    <category term="管理" />
    <category term="程序员" />
    <category term="职场" />
    <category term="人生" />
    <category term="物联网" />
    <category term="城市规划" />
    <category term="Python" />
    <category term="教孩子学编程" />
    <category term="创客" />
    <category term="比赛" />
    <category term="科技向善" />
    <category term="英语" />
    <category term="学习" />
    <category term="环保" />
    <category term="碳中和" />
    <category term="种植" />
    <category term="健身" />
    <category term="地理" />
    <category term="城市" />
    <category term="气象爱好者" />
    <category term="指南" />
    <category term="自律" />
    <category term="思维" />
    <category term="健康" />
    <category term="Hexo" />
    <category term="科普" />
    <category term="可持续" />
    <category term="能源" />
    <category term="职业" />
    <category term="时间管理" />
    <category term="milestone" />
    <category term="工作" />
    <category term="总结" />
    <category term="慈济" />
    <category term="生活" />
    <category term="RT-Thread" />
    <category term="开源" />
    <category term="写书" />
    <category term="修身" />
    <category term="思考" />
    <category term="幸福" />
    <category term="猫" />
    <category term="Markdown" />
    <category term="地铁" />
    <category term="计划" />
    <category term="股票" />
    <category term="理财" />
    <category term="投资" />
    <category term="财富" />
    <category term="保险" />
    <category term="纪录片" />
    <category term="自由" />
    <category term="电影" />
    <category term="定律" />
    <category term="心理学" />
    <category term="无线电爱好者" />
    <category term="亲密关系" />
    <category term="农业" />
    <category term="报告" />
    <category term="TED" />
    <category term="演讲" />
    <category term="励志" />
    <category term="时间" />
    <category term="游泳" />
    <category term="蔬食" />
    <category term="声音训练" />
    <category term="WordPress" />
    <category term="垃圾分类" />
    <category term="零废弃" />
    <category term="低碳" />
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/speech/grit-the-power-of-passion-and-perseverance.html</id>
        <title>【TED】坚韧不拔：激情和毅力的力量</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/speech/grit-the-power-of-passion-and-perseverance.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;演讲题目：Grit: The power of passion and perseverance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;演讲者：Angela Lee Duckworth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;中英双语版本&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#中英双语版本&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 中英双语版本&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=35473820&amp;bvid=BV1Fb411c7J7&amp;cid=62190294&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;无字幕原版&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#无字幕原版&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 无字幕原版&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=35473820&amp;bvid=BV1Fb411c7J7&amp;cid=62190447&amp;page=2&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;同名书籍&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#同名书籍&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 同名书籍&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;英文：《&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuYW1hem9uLmNvbS9Hcml0LVBhc3Npb24tUGVyc2V2ZXJhbmNlLUFuZ2VsYS1EdWNrd29ydGgvZHAvMTUwMTExMTEwOA==&#34;&gt;Grit: The Power of Passion and Perseverance&lt;/span&gt;》&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;繁体中文：《&lt;span class=&#34;exturl&#34; data-url=&#34;aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuYm9va3MuY29tLnR3L3Byb2R1Y3RzLzAwMTA4Njc5MzE=&#34;&gt;恆毅力：人生成功的究極能力&lt;/span&gt;》&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="TED" />
        <category term="演讲" />
        <category term="励志" />
        <updated>2023-03-02T04:56:58.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/speech/steve-jobs-2005-stanford-commencement-speech.html</id>
        <title>乔布斯：斯坦福大学 2005 毕业演讲</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/speech/steve-jobs-2005-stanford-commencement-speech.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;演讲视频&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#演讲视频&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 演讲视频&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=17203668&amp;bvid=BV1oW411h7Ea&amp;cid=28116082&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;演讲全文&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#演讲全文&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 演讲全文&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;感谢大家！&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am honored to be with you today at your commencement from one of the finest universities in the world. Truth be told, I never graduated from college, and this is the closest I’ve ever gotten to a college graduation. Today I want to tell you three stories from my life. That’s it. No big deal. Just three stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我今天很荣幸能和你们一起参加毕业典礼，斯坦福大学是世界上最好的大学之一。我从来没有从大学中毕业。说实话，今天也许是在我的生命中离大学毕业最近的一天了。今天我想向你们讲述我生活中的三个故事。不是什么大不了的事情，只是三个故事而已。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first story is about connecting the dots.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;第一个故事是关于如何把生命中的点点滴滴串连起来。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dropped out of Reed College after the first 6 months, but then stayed around as a drop-in for another 18 months or so before I really quit. So why did I drop out？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我在 Reed 大学读了六个月之后就退学了，但是在十八个月以后 —— 我真正的作出退学决定之前，我还经常去学校。我为什么要退学呢？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started before I was born. My biological mother was a young, unwed college graduate student, and she decided to put me up for adoption. She felt very strongly that I should be adopted by college graduates, so everything was all set for me to be adopted at birth by a lawyer and his wife. Except that when I popped out they decided at the last minute that they really wanted a girl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;故事从我出生的时候讲起。我的亲生母亲是一个年轻的，没有结婚的大学毕业生。她决定让别人收养我，她十分想让我被大学毕业生收养。所以在我出生的时候，她已经做好了一切的准备工作，能使得我被一个律师和他的妻子所收养。但是她没有料到，当我出生之后，律师夫妇突然决定他们想要一个女孩。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my parents, who were on a waiting list, got a call in the middle of the night asking: “We have an unexpected baby boy; do you want him？” They said: “Of course.” My biological mother later found out that my mother had never graduated from college and that my father had never graduated from high school. She refused to sign the final adoption papers. She only relented a few months later when my parents promised that I would someday go to college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以我的生养父母 (他们还在我亲生父母的观察名单上) 突然在半夜接到了一个电话:“我们现在这儿有一个不小心生出来的男婴，你们想要他吗？” 他们回答道:“当然！” 但是我亲生母亲随后发现，我的养母从来没有上过大学，我的父亲甚至从没有读过高中。她拒绝签这个收养合同。只是在几个月以后，我的父母答应她一定要让我上大学，那个时候她才同意。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And 17 years later I did go to college. But I naively chose a college that was almost as expensive as Stanford, and all of my working-class parents’ savings were being spent on my college tuition. After six months, I couldn’t see the value in it. I had no idea what I wanted to do with my life and no idea how college was going to help me figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在十七岁那年，我真的上了大学。但是我很愚蠢的选择了一个几乎和你们斯坦福大学一样贵的学校，我父母还处于蓝领阶层，他们几乎把所有积蓄都花在了我的学费上面。在六个月后，我已经看不到其中的价值所在。我不知道我想要在生命中做什么，我也不知道大学能帮助我找到怎样的答案。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here I was spending all of the money my parents had saved their entire life. So I decided to drop out and trust that it would all work out OK. It was pretty scary at the time, but looking back it was one of the best decisions I ever made. The minute I dropped out I could stop taking the required classes that didn’t interest me, and begin dropping in on the ones that looked interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是在这里，我几乎花光了我父母这一辈子的所有积蓄。所以我决定要退学，我觉得这是个正确的决定。不能否认，我当时确实非常的害怕，但是现在回头看看，那的确是我这一生中最棒的一个决定。在我做出退学决定的那一刻，我终于可以不必去读那些令我提不起丝毫兴趣的课程了。然后我还可以去修那些看起来有点意思的课程。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t all romantic. I didn’t have a dorm room, so I slept on the floor in friends’ rooms, I returned coke bottles for the 5¢ deposits to buy food with, and I would walk the 7 miles across town every Sunday night to get one good meal a week at the Hare Krishna temple. I loved it. And much of what I stumbled into by following my curiosity and intuition turned out to be priceless later on. Let me give you one example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是这并不是那么罗曼蒂克。我失去了我的宿舍，所以我只能在朋友房间的地板上面睡觉，我去捡 5 美分的可乐瓶子，仅仅为了填饱肚子，在星期天的晚上，我需要走七英里的路程，穿过这个城市到 Hare Krishna 寺庙 (注：位于纽约 Brooklyn 下城), 只是为了能吃上饭 —— 这个星期唯一一顿好一点的饭。但是我喜欢这样。我跟着我的直觉和好奇心走，遇到的很多东西，此后被证明是无价之宝。让我给你们举一个例子吧：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reed College at that time offered perhaps the best calligraphy instruction in the country. Throughout the campus every poster, every label on every drawer, was beautifully hand calligraphed. Because I had dropped out and didn’t have to take the normal classes, I decided to take a calligraphy class to learn how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reed 大学在那时提供也许是全美最好的美术字课程。在这个大学里面的每个海报，每个抽屉的标签上面全都是漂亮的美术字。因为我退学了，没有受到正规的训练，所以我决定去参加这个课程，去学学怎样写出漂亮的美术字。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned about serif and san serif typefaces, about varying the amount of space between different letter combinations, about what makes great typography great. It was beautiful, historical, artistically subtle in a way that science can’t capture, and I found it fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我学到了 san serif 和 serif 字体，我学会了怎么样在不同的字母组合之中改变空格的长度，还有怎么样才能作出最棒的印刷式样。那是一种科学永远不能捕捉到的、美丽的、真实的艺术精妙，我发现那实在是太美妙了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this had even a hope of any practical application in my life. But ten years later, when we were designing the first Macintosh computer, it all came back to me. And we designed it all into the Mac. It was the first computer with beautiful typography. If I had never dropped in on that single course in college, the Mac would have never had multiple typefaces or proportionally spaced fonts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当时看起来这些东西在我的生命中，好像都没有什么实际应用的可能。但是十年之后，当我们在设计第一台 Macintosh 电脑的时候，就不是那样了。我把当时我学的那些家伙全都设计进了 Mac。那是第一台使用了漂亮的印刷字体的电脑。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since Windows just copied the Mac, its likely that no personal computer would have them. If I had never dropped out, I would have never dropped in on this calligraphy class, and personal computers might not have the wonderful typography that they do. Of course it was impossible to connect the dots looking forward when I was in college. But it was very, very clear looking backwards ten years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果我当时没有退学，就不会有机会去参加这个我感兴趣的美术字课程，Mac 就不会有这么多丰富的字体，以及赏心悦目的字体间距。那么现在个人电脑就不会有现在这么美妙的字型了。当然我在大学的时候，还不可能把从前的点点滴 滴串连起来，但是当我十年后回顾这一切的时候，真的豁然开朗了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, you can’t connect the dots looking forward; you can only connect them looking backwards. So you have to trust that the dots will somehow connect in your future. You have to trust in something - your gut, destiny, life, karma, whatever. This approach has never let me down, and it has made all the difference in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;再次强调，没人可以未卜先知，事与事间的因和果，往往只在回首时显现。你得相信，因和果会在未来生活中联系起来。人总要有些信仰才行，直觉也好，命运也罢，因果轮回，不管什么，去相信因与果的联系，会给你信心去跟从自己的意愿，哪怕离经叛道，也绝不止步，只有这样，才能有所成就。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My second story is about love and loss.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;我的第二个故事是关于爱和损失的。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was lucky – I found what I loved to do early in life. Woz and I started Apple in my parents garage when I was 20. We worked hard, and in 10 years Apple had grown from just the two of us in a garage into a billion company with over 4000 employees. We had just released our finest creation - the Macintosh - a year earlier, and I had just turned 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我非常幸运，因为我在很早的时候就找到了我钟爱的东西。Woz 和我在二十岁的时候就在父母的车库里面开创了苹果公司。我们工作得很努力，十年之后，这个公司从那两个车库中的穷光蛋发展到了超过四千名的雇员、价值超过二十亿的大公司。在公司成立的第九年，我们刚刚发布了最好的产品，那就是 Macintosh。我也快要到三十岁了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I got fired. How can you get fired from a company you started？ Well, as Apple grew we hired someone who I thought was very talented to run the company with me, and for the first year or so things went well. But then our visions of the future began to diverge and eventually we had a falling out. When we did, our Board of Directors sided with him. So at 30 I was out. And very publicly out. What had been the focus of my entire adult life was gone, and it was devastating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在那一年，我被炒了鱿鱼。你怎么可能被你自己创立的公司炒了鱿鱼呢？ 嗯，在苹果快速成长的时候，我们雇用了一个很有天分的家伙和我一起管理这个公司，在最初的几年，公司运转的很好。但是后来我们对未来的看法发生了分歧，最终我们吵了起来。当争吵不可开交的时候，董事会站在了他的那一边。所以在三十岁的时候，我被炒了。在这么多人的眼皮下我被炒了。在而立之年，我生命的全部支柱离自己远去，这真是毁灭性的打击。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really didn’t know what to do for a few months. I felt that I had let the previous generation of entrepreneurs down - that I had dropped the baton as it was being passed to me. I met with David Packard and Bob Noyce and tried to apologize for screwing up so badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在最初的几个月里，我真是不知道该做些什么。我把从前的创业激情给丢了，我觉得自己让与我一同创业的人都很沮丧。我和 David Pack 和 Bob Boyce 见面，并试图向他们道歉。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a very public failure, and I even thought about running away from the valley. But something slowly began to dawn on me – I still loved what I did. The turn of events at Apple had not changed that one bit. I had been rejected, but I was still in love. And so I decided to start over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我把事情弄得糟糕透顶了。但是我渐渐发现了曙光，我仍然喜爱我从事的这些东西。苹果公司发生的这些事情丝毫的没有改变这些，一点也没有。我被驱逐了，但是我仍然钟爱它。所以我决定从头再来。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t see it then, but it turned out that getting fired from Apple was the best thing that could have ever happened to me. The heaviness of being successful was replaced by the lightness of being a beginner again, less sure about everything. It freed me to enter one of the most creative periods of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我当时没有觉察，但是事后证明，从苹果公司被炒是我这辈子发生的最棒的事情。因为，作为一个成功者的沉重感觉被作为一个创业者的轻松感觉所重新代替：对任何事情都不那么特别看重。这让我觉得如此自由，进入了我生命中最有创造力的一个阶段。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the next five years, I started a company named NeXT, another company named Pixar, and fell in love with an amazing woman who would become my wife. Pixar went on to create the worlds first computer animated feature film, Toy Story, and is now the most successful animation studio in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在接下来的五年里，我创立了一个名叫 NeXT 的公司，还有一个叫 Pixar 的公司，然后和一个后来成为我妻子的优雅女人相识。Pixar 制作了世界上第一个用电脑制作的动画电影 ——“玩具总动员”,Pixar 现在也是世界上最成功的电脑制作工作室。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a remarkable turn of events, Apple bought NeXT, I returned to Apple, and the technology we developed at NeXT is at the heart of Apple’s current renaissance. And Laurene and I have a wonderful family together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在后来的一系列运转中，Apple 收购了 NeXT, 然后我又回到了 Apple 公司。我们在 NeXT 发展的技术在 Apple 的复兴之中发挥了关键的作用。我还和 Laurence 一起建立了一个幸福的家庭。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure none of this would have happened if I hadn’t been fired from Apple. It was awful tasting medicine, but I guess the patient needed it. Sometimes life hits you in the head with a brick. Don’t lose faith. I’m convinced that the only thing that kept me going was that I loved what I did. You’ve got to find what you love. And that is as true for your work as it is for your lovers. Your work is going to fill a large part of your life, and the only way to be truly satisfied is to do what you believe is great work. And the only way to do great work is to love what you do. If you haven’t found it yet, keep looking. Don’t settle. As with all matters of the heart, you’ll know when you find it. And, like any great relationship, it just gets better and better as the years roll on. So keep looking until you find it. Don’t settle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我可以非常肯定，如果我不被 Apple 开除的话，这其中一件事情也不会发生的。这个良药的味道实在是太苦了，但是我想病人需要这个药。有时候生活会给你迎头一击，不要灰心丧气。我坚信，唯一可以让我坚持下去的，就是我对自己事业的热爱。你必须去寻找自己所爱，无论是工作还是爱情，都是如此。工作是生活中很主要的部分，真正获得满足感，就必须做你相信是有价值的工作。要做有价值的事业，你就必须热爱你做的事业，如果你还没找到，千万不要放弃，要继续寻找，只要倾听你的心声，当你真的发现时你就会感到，就像任何伟大的感情关系一样，岁月的更迭只会让这份情愈发深刻，所以千万不要放弃，要继续寻找。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My third story is about death.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;我的第三个故事是关于死亡的。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was 17, I read a quote that went something like: “If you live each day as if it was your last, someday you’ll most certainly be right.” It made an impression on me, and since then, for the past 33 years, I have looked in the mirror every morning and asked myself: “If today were the last day of my life, would I want to do what I am about to do today？” And whenever the answer has been “No” for too many days in a row, I know I need to change something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当我十七岁的时候，我读到了一句话:“如果你把每一天都当作生命中最后一天去生活的话，那么有一天你会发现你是正确的。” 这句话给我留下了深刻的印象。从那时开始，过了 33 年，我在每天早晨都会对着镜子问自己:“如果今天是我生命中的最后一天，你会不会完成你今天想做的事情呢？” 当答案连续很多次被给予 “不是” 的时候，我知道自己需要改变某些事情了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remembering that I’ll be dead soon is the most important tool I’ve ever encountered to help me make the big choices in life. Because almost everything – all external expectations, all pride, all fear of embarrassment or failure - these things just fall away in the face of death, leaving only what is truly important. Remembering that you are going to die is the best way I know to avoid the trap of thinking you have something to lose. You are already naked. There is no reason not to follow your heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;提醒自己人的生命有限，令我一生都受益非常，令我能在人生重大问题上做出抉择。因为一切的一切，一切追求，一切荣耀，一切惶恐，一些挫折，在死亡面前都会显得微不足道 ，剩下的才是最重要的事情。记住自己总会死去是避免自己被种种担心所羁绊的最好方法，既然将一无所有，还有什么理由不追随自己的内心。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a year ago I was diagnosed with cancer. I had a scan at 7:30 in the morning, and it clearly showed a tumor on my pancreas. I didn’t even know what a pancreas was. The doctors told me this was almost certainly a type of cancer that is incurable, and that I should expect to live no longer than three to six months. My doctor advised me to go home and get my affairs in order, which is doctor’s code for prepare to die. It means to try to tell your kids everything you thought you’d have the next 10 years to tell them in just a few months. It means to make sure everything is buttoned up so that it will be as easy as possible for your family. It means to say your goodbyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大概一年以前，我被诊断出癌症。我在早晨七点半做了一个检查，检查清楚的显示在我的胰腺有一个肿瘤。我当时都不知道胰腺是什么东西。医生告诉我那很可能是一种无法治愈的癌症，我还有三到六个月的时间活在这个世界上。我的医生叫我回家，然后整理好我的一切，那就是医生准备死亡的程序。那意味着你将要把未来十年对你小孩说的话在几个月里面说完.; 那意味着把每件事情都搞定，让你的家人会尽可能轻松的生活；那意味着你要说 “再见了”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lived with that diagnosis all day. Later that evening I had a biopsy, where they stuck an endoscope down my throat, through my stomach and into my intestines, put a needle into my pancreas and got a few cells from the tumor. I was sedated, but my wife, who was there, told me that when they viewed the cells under a microscope the doctors started crying because it turned out to be a very rare form of pancreatic cancer that is curable with surgery. I had the surgery and I’m fine now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我整天和那个诊断书一起生活。后来有一天早上我作了一个活切片检查，医生将一个内窥镜从我的喉咙伸进去，通过我的胃，然后进入我的肠子，用一根针在我的胰腺上的肿瘤上取了几个细胞。我当时很镇静，因为我被注射了镇定剂。但是我的妻子在那里，后来告诉我，当医生在显微镜地下观察这些细胞的时候他们开始尖叫，因为这些细胞最后竟然是一种非常罕见的可以用手术治愈的胰腺癌症。我做了这个手术，现在我痊愈了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the closest I’ve been to facing death, and I hope its the closest I get for a few more decades. Having lived through it, I can now say this to you with a bit more certainty than when death was a useful but purely intellectual concept:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;那是我最接近死亡的时候，我还希望这也是以后的几十年最接近的一次。从死亡线上又活了过来，死亡对我来说，只是一个有用但是纯粹是知识上的概念的时候，我可以更肯定一点地对你们说：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one wants to die. Even people who want to go to heaven don’t want to die to get there. And yet death is the destination we all share. No one has ever escaped it. And that is as it should be, because Death is very likely the single best invention of Life. It is Life’s change agent. It clears out the old to make way for the new. Right now the new is you, but someday not too long from now, you will gradually become the old and be cleared away. Sorry to be so dramatic, but it is quite true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;没有人愿意死，即使人们想上天堂，人们也不会为了去那里而死。但是死亡是我们每个人共同的终点。从来没有人能够逃脱它。也应该如此。 因为死亡就是生命中最好的一个发明。它将旧的清除以便给新的让路。你们现在是新的，但是从现在开始不久以后，你们将会逐渐的变成旧的然后被清除。我很抱歉这很戏剧性，但是这十分的真实。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your time is limited, so don’t waste it living someone else’s life. Don’t be trapped by dogma - which is living with the results of other people’s thinking. Don’t let the noise of other’s opinions drown out your own inner voice. And most important, have the courage to follow your heart and intuition. They somehow already know what you truly want to become. Everything else is secondary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;人生有限，所以不要把时间浪费在重复其他人的生活上；不要被教条束缚，那只是根据别人的思维结果而生活，不要让他人的喧嚣纷繁，淹没了自己内心的声音。最重要的是，你要有勇气去跟随你的直觉和心灵，因为它们在某种程度上已经知道你想要成为什么样子，所有其他的事情都是次要的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was young, there was an amazing publication called The Whole Earth Catalog, which was one of the bibles of my generation. It was created by a fellow named Stewart Brand not far from here in Menlo Park, and he brought it to life with his poetic touch. This was in the late 1960’s, before personal computers and desktop publishing, so it was all made with typewriters, scissors, and polaroid cameras. It was sort of like Google in paperback form, 35 years before Google came along: it was idealistic, and overflowing with neat tools and great notions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在我年轻的时候，有本很棒的叫全球目录的杂志。被我们那代人奉为经典。它是由斯图尔特・布兰德在这附近的 Menlo 公园创办的。他把自己的文艺气质融汇其中。那是六十年代后期。那时还没有个人电脑。全用打字机，剪刀和宝丽来照相机。它就好比是三十五年前的简装版的谷歌。充满理想主义色彩。该书简洁实用，见解独到。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stewart and his team put out several issues of The Whole Earth Catalog, and then when it had run its course, they put out a final issue. It was the mid-1970s, and I was your age. On the back cover of their final issue was a photograph of an early morning country road, the kind you might find yourself hitchhiking on if you were so adventurous. Beneath it were the words: “Stay Hungry. Stay Foolish.” It was their farewell message as they signed off. Stay Hungry. Stay Foolish. And I have always wished that for myself. And now, as you graduate to begin anew, I wish that for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay Hungry. Stay Foolish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you all very much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;斯图尔特团队出版了几期的全球目录。当它后来要停刊的时候，他们出来最后一版。那是七十年代中期，我就像你们这么大。杂志最后一期的封底上，是一幅清晨乡村公路的照片。是那种搭车旅行玩冒险时会遇到的村路，照片下面有这样一段话：求知若渴，虚心若愚。这是他们停刊的告别语。求知若渴，虚心若愚。我一直以此激励自己。在你们即将毕业开始崭新旅程的时刻，我希望你们也能做到：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;求知若渴，虚心若愚。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;谢谢大家！&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="演讲" />
        <category term="励志" />
        <updated>2022-10-07T03:44:57.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/speech/ted-you-dont-need-more-than-two-years.html</id>
        <title>【TED】改变自己，只需要两年时间</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/speech/ted-you-dont-need-more-than-two-years.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;视频-you-dont-need-more-than-two-years&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#视频-you-dont-need-more-than-two-years&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 视频 You don’t Need More Than Two Years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=883417381&amp;bvid=BV1TK4y1b77M&amp;cid=199198207&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;中英文对照&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#中英文对照&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 中英文对照&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;两年可以做什么&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#两年可以做什么&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 两年可以做什么&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years is nothing, but at the same time, a lot can be accomplished in two years. You can try a sport you’ve always wanted to start, and become a great at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两年时间不算什么，但在这段时间里，我们可以做很多事情。你可以尝试练习一项你一直想要开始的运动，然后成为一名高手。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start a morning routine, and affect your mood and stress at a deep level. You can meditate for a few minutes per day, become more self-aware and change the way you react to problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你可以开始制定某项早间习惯，它会从深层次影响你的情绪和压力。你每天可以冥想一分钟，这样就可以加强自我意识，提高应对问题的能力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can start a business and make it a big success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你可以开创一项事业，并让它走向成功。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years is nothing and extremely easy to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but with small actions , substantial commitment and consistency, you can make it count, a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两年的时间不算什么，也很容易浪费掉，但只要有微小的行动、实质性的付出和坚持，你就可以让它变得更有价值。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years being passive is a blink of an eye. Two years moving towards goals every single day is plenty of time. It’s just a matter of perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;消极度日，两年转眼即逝。每天有目标地前进，两年就意味着更多的时间。这仅仅是看问题的角度不同而已。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing that cannot be accomplished in two years with enough effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果足够努力，没有什么事情是两年内不能实现的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;开始做想做的事情&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#开始做想做的事情&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 开始做想做的事情&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start something you’ve wanted to do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;开始做你一直想做的事情&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re not too old for the things you were dreaming of doing when you were a kid. You can still do extreme sports if you wish to. You can start playing a musical instrument. You can become a photographer. In two years from now, you’ll be great at it if you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;对你年少时的梦想来说，你永远不会太老。只要你想，你还是能去做极限运动。你还是能去学习乐器。你还是能成为一名摄影师。从现在起的两年时间，只要你真的想要，你就能变得很厉害。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t let your past indicate who you are. You don’t have to be the same person you have always been. Don’t let fear control you. Don’t let the social standards conform you. Age is just a number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不要让你的过去决定你是谁。你也不必一直和以前一样。不要让恐惧支配你。不要让社会标准囚禁你。年龄只是个数字而已。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should all empower our uniqueness and fight against our own limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我们所有人都应赋予我们独特性，并与自己的局限作斗争。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing things you love on daily basis even for a few minutes, you’ll learn to enjoy the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每天去做你喜欢做的事情，哪怕只有几分钟，你也会享受这个过程。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The days will become more than just a means to an end. You’ll see yourself evolving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每天会变得更有意义，不会被虚度。你也会看到自己的进步。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;保持自律&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#保持自律&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 保持自律&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be in control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;保持自律&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the choice between feeling great, energetic and in a positive mood, versus feeling sleepy and moody, what would you choose? It’s just a choice which combined with small, even tiny actions like reducing meat or alcohol consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果你能选择让自己感觉棒棒的，精力旺盛，乐观向上，亦或是疲惫着，喜怒无常，你会选哪一个？这就是个简单的选择，再加上小小的行动比如少吃肉或少喝酒.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or simply drinking more water, walking the stairs or biking to the office, you can do wonders. It’s not about the end goal, it’s about daily actions towards it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;再或是多喝点水，爬楼梯或骑脚踏车上班，你就会创造奇迹了。这么做不是为了简单地达到目标，而是为了每天都能够朝这个方向进步。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also the reason why morning routines, or ten minutes daily meditation sessions are bringing such great changes in terms of mood, productivity, stress management, ect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这也是为什么早间的习惯和十分钟的每日冥想都能带给人巨大的改变，比如情绪、生产力和压力管理能力的改善。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replace TV shows and movies by documentaries and books. Minitor your days more getting control of how you spend your time. Take back the control of your health, mood and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;用纪录片和书籍取代电视节目和电影。加强监督自己的日常，控制自己利用时间的方式。夺回你对健康、情绪和时间的掌控权。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practive gratefulness. See the results in two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;学会感激。两年后见分晓。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;压制你的自负&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#压制你的自负&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 压制你的自负&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silence your ego&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;压制你的自负&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be kind with people. Start with your family, don’t go mad one more time. Stop judging, see the good in them, and remember that you love them more than anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;善待他人，再也不要和家人发火。停止批判，看见他们好的那面，并记得你爱他们超过一切。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your working life, being kind and nice can bring you more respect from people who surround you than being bossy and aggressive. Learn to say ‘No’ often (for the right reasons), people will accept it more and value your ‘Yes’ more, because your times’ value will increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在职场上，与人为善，相比发号施令和争强好胜，这会让你周围的人更尊重你。学会在正当理由下多说 “不”，这样人们会更容易接受，且更看重你说的 “好”，因为你的时间价值会增加。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to be scary to be respected. It’s about building trust and healthy long term relationships. Try this and in two years from now your reality will be so different. Silence your ego, love and trust others enough for two years, harvest for ten years or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你不用通过变得吓人去获得尊重。重点是要建立起相互信任且健康的长期关系。试试看，从现在开始起的两年，你的生活将会变得大不同。用两年时间去压制你的自负，去爱和信任他人，十年甚至更长的时间你都会因此受益。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;设定一个长期的目标&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#设定一个长期的目标&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 设定一个长期的目标&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set long term goals and do small actions everyday towards them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;设定一个长期的目标，然后坚持每天即便是微小的行动。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has a lot to do with setting goals, but goals without actions are just wishes. The easiest way to reach goals is through daily and consistent small (even tiny) actions. It’s all about consistency, commitment, and regularity. Success is not an event, it’s a process and a mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这和目标的设定有很大的关系，但光有目标没有行动就只能是美好的愿望而已。最简单达成目标的方法就是，每天都坚持微小的行动。一切都在于要建立一致性、要坚持付出和养成规律。成功不是一个偶然事件，它是个长久的过程和心态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small actions are putting you in the position of succeeding. Small actions make huge differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;微小的行动能让你走向成功的道路。微小的行动能带来巨大的改变。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at yourself in the mirror in two years and you’ll think ‘that was quick’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两年后在镜子中看看自己，你会想 “时间过的真快”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every day counts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;每一天都很重要。&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="TED" />
        <category term="演讲" />
        <category term="时间" />
        <updated>2021-09-07T14:47:18.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://luhuadong.com/speech/ted-why-30-is-not-the-new-20.html</id>
        <title>【TED】20岁到30岁，是你最不可挥霍的光阴</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://luhuadong.com/speech/ted-why-30-is-not-the-new-20.html"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;视频&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#视频&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 视频&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why 30 is not the new 20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=54802233&amp;bvid=BV1B4411K7Rb&amp;cid=95852081&amp;page=1&amp;high_quality=1&amp;danmaku=0&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; sandbox=&#34;allow-top-navigation allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;中英文对照&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;markdownIt-Anchor&#34; href=&#34;#中英文对照&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt; 中英文对照&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was in my 20s, I saw my very first psychotherapy client. I was a Ph.D. student in clinical psychology at Berkeley. She was a 26-year-old woman named Alex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;记得见我第一位心理咨询顾客时，我才 20 多岁。当时我是 Berkeley 临床心理学在读博士生。我的第一位顾客是名叫 Alex 的女性，26 岁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Alex walked into her first session wearing jeans and a big slouchy top, and she dropped onto the couch in my office and kicked off her flats and told me she was there to talk about guy problems. Now when I heard this, I was so relieved. My classmate got an arsonist for her first client. (Laughter) And I got a twentysomething who wanted to talk about boys. This I thought I could handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第一次见面 Alex 穿着牛仔裤和宽松上衣走进来，她一下子栽进我办公室的沙发上，踢掉脚上的平底鞋，跟我说她想谈谈男生的问题。当时我听到这个之后松了一口气。因为我同学的第一个顾客是纵火犯，而我的顾客却是一个 20 出头想谈谈男生的女孩。我觉得我可以搞定。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I didn’t handle it. With the funny stories that Alex would bring to session, it was easy for me just to nod my head while we kicked the can down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是我没有搞定。Alex 不断地讲有趣的事情，而我只能简单地点头认同她所说的，很自然地就陷入了附和的状态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thirty’s the new 20,” Alex would say, and as far as I could tell, she was right. Work happened later, marriage happened later, kids happened later, even death happened later. Twentysomethings like Alex and I had nothing but time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex 说：“30 岁是一个新的 20 岁”。没错，我告诉她 “你是对的”。工作还早，结婚还早，生孩子还早，甚至死亡也早着呢。像 Alex 和我这样 20 多岁的人，什么都没有但时间多的是。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before long, my supervisor pushed me to push Alex about her love life. I pushed back. I said, “Sure, she’s dating down, she’s sleeping with a knucklehead, but it’s not like she’s going to marry the guy.” And then my supervisor said, “Not yet, but she might marry the next one. Besides, the best time to work on Alex’s marriage is before she has one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但不久之后，我的导师就要我向 Alex 的感情生活施压。我反驳说：“当然她现在正在和别人交往，她现在和一个傻瓜男生睡觉，但看样子她不会和他结婚的。” 而我的导师说：“不着急，她也许会和下一个结婚。但修复 Alex 婚姻的最好时期是她还没拥有婚姻的时期。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what psychologists call an “Aha!” moment. That was the moment I realized, 30 is not the new 20. Yes, people settle down later than they used to, but that didn’t make Alex’s 20s a developmental downtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这就是心理学家说的 “顿悟时刻”。正是那个时候我意识到，30 岁不是一个新的 20 岁。的确，和以前的人相比，现在人们更晚才安定下来，但是这不代表 Alex 就能长期处于 20 多岁的状态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That made Alex’s 20s a developmental sweet spot, and we were sitting there blowing it. That was when I realized that this sort of benign neglect was a real problem, and it had real consequences, not just for Alex and her love life but for the careers and the families and the futures of twentysomethings everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;更晚安定下来，应该使 Alex 的 20 多岁成为发展的黄金时段，而我们却坐在那里忽视这个发展的时机。从那时起我意识到这种善意的忽视确实是个问题，它不仅给 Alex 本身和她的感情生活带来不良后果，而且影响到处 20 多岁的人的事业、家庭和未来。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 50 million twentysomethings in the United States right now. We’re talking about 15 percent of the population, or 100 percent if you consider that no one’s getting through adulthood without going through their 20s first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;现在在美国，20 多岁的人有五千万，也就是 15% 的人口，或者可以说所有人口，因为所有成年人都要经历他们的 20 多岁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raise your hand if you’re in your 20s. I really want to see some twentysomethings here. Oh, yay! Y’all’s awesome. If you work with twentysomethings, you love a twentysomething, you’re losing sleep over twentysomethings, I want to see — Okay. Awesome, twentysomethings really matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果你现在 20 多岁，请举手。我很想看到有 20 多岁的人在这里。哦，很好。如果你和 20 多岁的人一起工作，你喜欢 20 多岁的人，你因为 20 多岁的人辗转难眠，我想看到你们。很棒，看来 20 多岁的人确实很受重视。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I specialize in twentysomethings because I believe that every single one of those 50 million twentysomethings deserves to know what psychologists, sociologists, neurologists and fertility specialists already know: that claiming your 20s is one of the simplest, yet most transformative, things you can do for work, for love, for your happiness, maybe even for the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此我专门研究 20 多岁的人，因为我坚信这五千万的 20 多岁的人，每一个人都应该去了解那些心理学家、社会学家、神经学家和生育专家已经知道的事实：你的 20 多岁是极简单却极具变化的时期之一。你 20 多岁的时光决定了你的事业、爱情、幸福甚至整个世界。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not my opinion. These are the facts. We know that 80 percent of life’s most defining moments take place by age 35. That means that eight out of 10 of the decisions and experiences and “Aha!” moments that make your life what it is will have happened by your mid-30s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这不是我的看法。这些是事实。我们知道 80% 决定你生活的时刻发生在 35 岁之前。这就意味着你生活的重要决定、经历和突然的领悟，有八成是在你 30 多岁之前发生的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who are over 40, don’t panic. This crowd is going to be fine, I think. We know that the first 10 years of a career has an exponential impact on how much money you’re going to earn. We know that more than half of Americans are married or are living with or dating their future partner by 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;那些超过 40 岁的朋友不要惊慌，我想这群人会没事的。我们知道职业生涯的前 10 年对你将来的收入有重大影响。我们知道到了 30 岁的时候，超过半数的美国人会结婚或者和未来的另一半同居或者约会。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that the brain caps off its second and last growth spurt in your 20s as it rewires itself for adulthood, which means that whatever it is you want to change about yourself, now is the time to change it. We know that personality changes more during your 20s than at any other time in life, and we know that female fertility peaks at age 28, and things get tricky after age 35.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我们知道人在 20 多岁的时候大脑停止第二次也是最后一次重组，以适应成年世界的快速发育阶段。这就意味着不管你想怎样改变自己，现在就是时间改变了。我们知道在 20 多岁的时候，性格的改变多于生命中任何时期。我们也知道女性的最佳生育时期在 28 岁的时候达到顶峰，35 岁之后生育变得困难。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So your 20s are the time to educate yourself about your body and your options. So when we think about child development, we all know that the first five years are a critical period for language and attachment in the brain. It’s a time when your ordinary, day-to-day life has an inordinate impact on who you will become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以你的 20 多岁正是了解你自身和选择的时期。当我们想到孩童的成长时，我们都知道 1-5 岁是大脑学习语言和感知的重要时期。这个时期，日常的普通生活都会对你的未来道路影响巨大。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what we hear less about is that there’s such a thing as adult development, and our 20s are that critical period of adult development. But this isn’t what twentysomethings are hearing. Newspapers talk about the changing timetable of adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是我们却很少听到成年发展期，而我们的 20 多岁正是成年发展期的关键。但是 20 多岁的人却听不到这些，报纸讨论的只是成年年龄界线的变更。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers call the 20s an extended adolescence. Journalists coin silly nicknames for twentysomethings like “twixters” and “kidults.” It’s true. As a culture, we have trivialized what is actually the defining decade of adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;研究者称 20 多岁是延长的青春期。记者就引用傻傻的外号称呼 20 多岁的人，比如 “twixters” (twenty-mixters) 和 “kidults”(kid-adults)。 这是真的。作为一种文化，我们的忽视的正是对成年起到决定性作用的十年（从 20 岁到 30 岁）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard Bernstein said that to achieve great things, you need a plan and not quite enough time. Isn’t that true? So what do you think happens when you pat a twentysomething on the head and you say, “You have 10 extra years to start your life”? Nothing happens. You have robbed that person of his urgency and ambition, and absolutely nothing happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;雷昂纳德・伯恩斯坦说过：要想取得成就，你需要一个计划和紧迫的时间。这是大实话啊！所以当你拍着一个 20 多岁的人的脑袋，跟他说，“你有额外的 10 年去开始你的生活”，你觉得这改变了什么？什么都没改变。你只是夺走了那个人的紧迫感和雄心壮志，绝对没有改变什么。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then every day, smart, interesting twentysomethings like you or like your sons and daughters come into my office and say things like this: “I know my boyfriend’s no good for me, but this relationship doesn’t count. I’m just killing time.” Or they say, “Everybody says as long as I get started on a career by the time I’m 30, I’ll be fine.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然后每天，那些聪明有趣的 20 多岁的人就像你们和你们的儿子女儿一样，走入我的办公室开始说：“我知道我的男朋友对我不够好，但是我们的关系不算数。我只是在消磨时光而已。” 或者说 “每个人都告诉我只要能在 30 岁的时候开始我的事业，这就足够了。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then it starts to sound like this: “My 20s are almost over, and I have nothing to show for myself. I had a better résumé the day after I graduated from college.” And then it starts to sound like this: &amp;quot;Dating in my 20s was like musical chairs. Everybody was running around and having fun, but then sometime around 30 it was like the music turned off and everybody started sitting down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是实际听上去却是：“我马上就要三十了，却根本就没有东西展示。我只是在大学毕业时有过一份最漂亮的简历。” 或是这样：“我 20 多岁时的约会就像找凳子。每个人都绕着凳子跑，随便玩一玩，但是快 30 的时候就像音乐停止了，所有人开始坐下。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to be the only one left standing up, so sometimes I think I married my husband because he was the closest chair to me at 30.&amp;quot; Where are the twentysomethings here? Do not do that. Okay, now that sounds a little flip, but make no mistake, the stakes are very high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我不想成为那唯一站着的人，所以有时候我会想我和我丈夫之所以会结婚，是因为在我 30 岁的时候，他是当时离我最近的那张凳子。在场的 20 多岁的人呐，千万不要这样做。这个做法听起来有点轻率，但是不要犯错，因为风险很高。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a lot has been pushed to your 30s, there is enormous thirtysomething pressure to jump-start a career, pick a city, partner up, and have two or three kids in a much shorter period of time. Many of these things are incompatible, and as research is just starting to show, simply harder and more stressful to do all at once in our 30s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当很多事都被挤到你 30 多岁的时候，就会有巨大压力，在很短的时间内快速启动一项事业，挑一个城市，找到伴侣，生两三个孩子。这些事大多是不能同时完成的，正如研究表明，在 30 岁的时候要想工作生活一步到位，难度很高，压力很大。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-millennial midlife crisis isn’t buying a red sports car. It’s realizing you can’t have that career you now want. It’s realizing you can’t have that child you now want, or you can’t give your child a sibling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;千禧年后的中年危机并不是一辆红色跑车。而是意识到你不能拥有你想拥有的事业，意识到你不能拥有你想要的孩子，或者给你的孩子添个兄弟姐妹。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too many thirtysomethings and fortysomethings look at themselves, and at me, sitting across the room, and say about their 20s, “What was I doing? What was I thinking?” I want to change what twentysomethings are doing and thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;太多 30 多岁 40 多岁的人看看他们自己，看看我，坐在屋子里谈论自己的 20 多岁，“我当时都干么了？我当时都想啥了？” 我想改变现在 20 多岁人的所思所为。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a story about how that can go. It’s a story about a woman named Emma. At 25, Emma came to my office because she was, in her words, having an identity crisis. She said she thought she might like to work in art or entertainment, but she hadn’t decided yet, so she’d spent the last few years waiting tables instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这里我想讲个故事说明问题。这个故事是关于名叫 Emma 一个女人。她 25 岁的时候走入我的办公室，因为用她自己的话说，她有自我认识危机。她说她也许想从事关于艺术或者娱乐的工作，但是她还没决定。所以取而代之的是她花了过去几年的时间当服务员。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it was cheaper, she lived with a boyfriend who displayed his temper more than his ambition. And as hard as her 20s were, her early life had been even harder. She often cried in our sessions, but then would collect herself by saying, “You can’t pick your family, but you can pick your friends.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;为了减少开销，她和她的男朋友同居，一个脾气暴躁而无志向的人。正如她悲惨的 20 多岁，她早年的生活更加悲惨。她经常在谈话过程中哭泣，努力镇定下来后说 “你没办法选择你的家庭，但是你可以选择你的朋友。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well one day, Emma comes in and she hangs her head in her lap, and she sobbed for most of the hour. She’d just bought a new address book, and she’d spent the morning filling in her many contacts, but then she’d been left staring at that empty blank that comes after the words &amp;quot;In case of emergency, please call … &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有一天，Emma 走进来，她双手抱头于膝盖，然后抽泣了几乎一个小时。她刚买了一个新的通讯录本子，然后花了一整个早上的时间填写她的联系人信息。当她填到 “万一发生紧急情况，请联系…” 的时候，她没有任何人可填。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was nearly hysterical when she looked at me and said, “Who’s going to be there for me if I get in a car wreck? Who’s going to take care of me if I have cancer?” Now in that moment, it took everything I had not to say, “I will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;她几乎崩溃地看着我并说，“如果我被车撞了，谁会在那里？假如我得癌症了，谁会在那里？” 在那种情况下，我花了好大力气才忍住说 “我会。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what Emma needed wasn’t some therapist who really, really cared. Emma needed a better life, and I knew this was her chance. I had learned too much since I first worked with Alex to just sit there while Emma’s defining decade went parading by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma 所需要的并不是理疗师所真正关心的。她需要一个更好的生活，我知道这是她的机会。自 Alex 开始，我从这份工作上学到了很多，不能只是坐在那里看着 Emma 十年黄金定型期白白消逝。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So over the next weeks and months, I told Emma three things that every twentysomething, male or female, deserves to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以接下去的几个星期几个月，我告诉 Emma 三件事，所有 20 多岁的男生女生都值得听一听。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I told Emma to forget about having an identity crisis and get some identity capital. By get identity capital, I mean do something that adds value to who you are. Do something that’s an investment in who you might want to be next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;首先，我告诉 Emma 忘掉她的自我认识危机，去获得一些身份认定的资本。身份资本是指做增加自我价值的事。为自己下一步想成为的样子做一些事一些投资。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know the future of Emma’s career, and no one knows the future of work, but I do know this: Identity capital begets identity capital. So now is the time for that cross-country job, that internship, that startup you want to try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我不知道 Emma 的工作将来是什么样的，也没人知道将来的工作是什么样的，但是我知道：身份资本会创造出更多身份资本。现在是时候去尝试你想要的海外工作、实习或者新起点。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not discounting twentysomething exploration here, but I am discounting exploration that’s not supposed to count, which, by the way, is not exploration. That’s procrastination. I told Emma to explore work and make it count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我不是轻视 20 多岁的自我探索，而是轻视那些随便玩玩无所谓的探索，或者从某种意义上说那不是探索。那是拖沓！我告诉 Emma 去探索工作，让她的探索有所回报。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I told Emma that the urban tribe is overrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第二，我告诉 Emma 不要高估自己的朋友圈。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best friends are great for giving rides to the airport, but twentysomethings who huddle together with like-minded peers limit who they know, what they know, how they think, how they speak, and where they work. That new piece of capital, that new person to date almost always comes from outside the inner circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;好朋友会载你去机场，而和 “志同道合的朋友” 瞎混的 20 多岁的人，他们的交际圈、知识面、思维方式、说话方式和工作层面都被限制住了。新的资本或者新的约会对方往往是从内部交际圈之外来的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New things come from what are called our weak ties, our friends of friends of friends. So yes, half of twentysomethings are un- or under-employed. But half aren’t, and weak ties are how you get yourself into that group. Half of new jobs are never posted, so reaching out to your neighbor’s boss is how you get that un-posted job. It’s not cheating. It’s the science of how information spreads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;新的事情来自我们所谓的 “弱关系”，我们朋友的朋友的朋友。没错，半数 20 多岁的人处在失业和半失业的状态。但是另外一半的人却不是这样的，“弱关系” 正是你融入一个新的群体的纽带。有半数的新工作从来不公示出来，所以联络你邻居的老板是你找到那些未公示工作的方式。这不叫作弊，这是信息传播的科学方式。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, Emma believed that you can’t pick your family, but you can pick your friends. Now this was true for her growing up, but as a twentysomething, soon Emma would pick her family when she partnered with someone and created a family of her own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;最后一点也很重要，Emma 相信你无法选择你的家庭，但是你可以选择你的朋友。可这只是她成长时期的状况。作为一个 20 多岁的人，Emma 很快会与某人为伴组建她自己的新家庭。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I told Emma the time to start picking your family is now. Now you may be thinking that 30 is actually a better time to settle down than 20, or even 25, and I agree with you. But grabbing whoever you’re living with or sleeping with when everyone on Facebook starts walking down the aisle is not progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我告诉 Emma 现在就是你选择你家庭的时候。现在你也许会想相比于 20 岁，25 岁或 30 岁时组建家庭会更好。我同意你的看法。但是当你 Facebook 上的朋友都开始步入婚姻殿堂时，你随便抓一个人一起生活、睡觉绝对不是组建家庭的过程。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to work on your marriage is before you have one, and that means being as intentional with love as you are with work. Picking your family is about consciously choosing who and what you want rather than just making it work or killing time with whoever happens to be choosing you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;经营你婚姻的最佳时间是你还没结婚的时候，这意味要像你为了工作一样精心谋划。选择你的家庭是有意识地去选择你想要的人和事，而不是为了结婚或者消磨时光，任意选择一个正好选择你的人。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happened to Emma? Well, we went through that address book, and she found an old roommate’s cousin who worked at an art museum in another state. That weak tie helped her get a job there. That job offer gave her the reason to leave that live-in boyfriend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma 发生了什么变化呢？我们翻了一遍通讯录，她发现她原来的舍友的表妹在另一个州的一家艺术博物馆工作。这层弱关系帮助她在那里得到一份工作。这份工作给她一个理由离开她那同居的男友。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, five years later, she’s a special events planner for museums. She’s married to a man she mindfully chose. She loves her new career, she loves her new family, and she sent me a card that said, “Now the emergency contact blanks don’t seem big enough.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;现在五年过去了，她是一名博物馆特别活动策划者。她和一个她用心选择的男人结婚了。她爱她的事业，她爱她的新家，她寄给我一张贺卡写道，“现在紧急联系栏似乎不够填呢。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Emma’s story made that sound easy, but that’s what I love about working with twentysomethings. They are so easy to help. Twentysomethings are like airplanes just leaving LAX, bound for somewhere west. Right after takeoff, a slight change in course is the difference between landing in Alaska or Fiji.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emma 的故事听起来简单，这正是为什么我爱和 20 多岁人打交道。帮助 20 多岁的人很容易。20 多岁就像离开洛杉矶飞往西部某处的飞机，起飞之后，一点小小变化都会影响到它最终将降落在阿拉斯加还是斐济。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, at 21 or 25 or even 29, one good conversation, one good break, one good TED Talk, can have an enormous effect across years and even generations to come. So here’s an idea worth spreading to every twentysomething you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;同理，在你 21 岁，25 岁甚至 29 岁的时候，一次好的谈话、好的休息、好的 TED 演讲，能在未来的几年甚至几代人的时间里带来巨大的影响。因此这个想法值得传达给每一个你所认识的 20 多岁人。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as what I learned to say to Alex. It’s what I now have the privilege of saying to twentysomethings like Emma every single day: Thirty is not the new 20, so claim your adulthood, get some identity capital, use your weak ties, pick your family. Don’t be defined by what you didn’t know or didn’t do. You’re deciding your life right now. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这想法就像我后来告诉 Alex 的话一样简单。我应该每天都对像 Emma 这样的 20 多岁的人说：30 岁不是一个新的 20 岁，所以规划好你的成年生活，获得一些身份认同资本，利用你的弱关系，选择你的家庭。不要被你所不知道的，从未做过的事所禁锢。你现在的作为决定着你的人生。谢谢。&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="TED" />
        <category term="演讲" />
        <category term="时间" />
        <updated>2020-05-18T14:47:18.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
</feed>
